# Alessandro larcomini

MSc in Physics of Data University of Padova

Via Rovaia 28, 32100 Belluno (BL), Italy (+39) 329-871-8070 ⊠ marcomini.ales@gmail.com



I am a 23 years old graduate student of Physics of Data with great interest in data analysis, machine learning, and quantum technologies.

I believe in the power of communication, that curiosity is the highway to the future and that laziness is the strongest engine of human kind.

#### Education

2020-present Master's Degree in Physics of Data, University of Padova GPA - 3.92/4.00

2017–2020 Bachelor's Degree in Physics, University of Padova GPA - 3.71/4.00

2017–2022 University College of Merit, Collegio Don Nicola Mazza Head of students' council, communication manager, over 600 hours of extra-academic activities including seminars, courses and non-formal education.

2012–2017 Scientific High School Diploma, Liceo G.Galilei, Belluno (BL) Final evaluation: 100/100

## Experience

#### Internships

2022-present Assistant Student - Quantum Optimal Control, Forschungszentrum Jülich I am working in the PGI-8 institute supervised by Prof. Tommaso Calarco. Goals:

- Design efficient tools for optimal control of two-qubit gates for quantum computing
- Numerical simulations of dCRAB optimization in NV-centers in diamonds

Summer Visiting Student - Ultracold atoms in optical traps, IAP, Bonn University

2021 I worked in the group of Prof. Dieter Meschede. Achievements:

- Tuned experimental set-up to trap atoms in 3D optical lattices
- Enhanced laser beams performances via optical path alignment

2020 Bachelor's Thesis - Hacking the implementation of QKD, LUXOR laboratories, University of Padova

I worked in the group of Prof. Paolo Villoresi. Achievements:

- Review quantum attacks on both ends of quantum key distribution systems
- Proposed quantitative countermeasures to enhance security of POGNAC devices

- 2020-2021 Innovation Experience Contamination Lab, Collegio Don Nicola Mazza I took part in an educational program about the world of start-ups and entrepreneurship Work Experience
  - 2021 Business Design innovator, MED Health Technologies, Maserà, PD, Italy
- 2019–2020 Mathematics TA, Collegio Don Nicola Mazza, Padova, PD, Italy
- 2018–2020 Audio-Video technician, Collegio Don Nicola Mazza, Padova, PD, Italy
- 2018–2019 Librarian, University of Padova, Padova, PD, Italy
- 2016–2018 Volleyball Referee, FIPAV Veneto, Belluno, BL, Italy

# Computer Skills

**Proficent:** Python, R, LATEX, Miscrosoft Office, **Confident:** Fortran, C++, VHDL, Qiskit, **To be refreshed:** Root, Spark, C#, Q#

# Languages

Italian (Mother tongue), English (IELTS, C1 level, 2021) French (DELF, B1 level, 2018)

### Honors and Awards

- 2021 Quantum Coalition Hackathon Winner of Microsoft's challenge, Stanford University and Yale University
  In team, we developed a quantum game in Q# exploiting Grover's search algorithm
- 2021 Qiskit Quantum Summer School certificate of Quantum Excellence, Quantum Machine Learning, IBM Quantum
- 2021 **Gamification Hackathon Winning team**, Collegio Don Nicola Mazza We designed a platform to ease university students life following gamification techniques
- 2022 European Spring School in Quantum Science and Technology Selected Participant, University of Strasbourg
- 2019 Pan-European Quantum Internet Hackathon Participant, CERN

#### Passions and Interests

- Internationality: I took part in five Erasmus+ projects all over Europe and I collaborate as project writer and group leader with a local association
- Drama: since 10 years I perform in multiple plays both in Italian and English
- Sports: I enjoy all team sports; I used to play football, volleyball and chess
- Music: I used to play the piano and I self-taught myself how to play ukulele
- Disseminations: I enjoy sharing my knowledge with newbies in events

## Community Activities

- Scout group: 10 years of activities both as mentee and mentor
- **Environment**: founder member of the informal group "Sustainable Vibes", to favor active youth actions on the topic
- Volunteering: member of three no-profit local organizations